Matthew 18
At that time the disciples came to Jesus, saying,
Who is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven?
And calling to him a child, he put him in the midst of them and said,
Truly I say to you, unless you turn and become like children, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven.
Whoever humbles himself like this child is the greatest in the kingdom of heaven.
Whoever receives one such child in my name receives me.
But whoever causes one of these little ones who believe in me to sin,
it would be better for him to have a great millstone fastened around his neck
and to be drowned in the depth of the sea.
Woe to the world for temptations to sin, for it is necessary that temptations come.
But woe to the one by whom the temptation comes.
And if your hand or your foot...
If your foot causes you to sin, cut it off and throw it away.
It is better for you to enter life crippled or lame
than with two hands or two feet to be thrown into the eternal fire.
And if your eye causes you to sin, tear it out and throw it away.
It is better for you to enter life with one eye
than with two eyes to be thrown into the hell of fire.
See that you do not despise one of these little ones.
For I tell you that in heaven their angels...
I see the face of my Father who is in heaven.
What do you think?
If a man has a hundred sheep and one of them has gone astray,
does he not leave the ninety-nine on the mountains
and go in search of the one that went astray?
And if he finds it, truly I say to you,
he rejoices over it more than over the ninety-nine that never went astray.
So it is not the will of my Father who is in heaven
that one of these little ones should perish.
If your...
If your brother sins against you,
go and tell him his fault, between you and him alone.
If he listens to you, you have gained your brother.
But if he does not listen, take one or two others along with you,
that every charge may be established by the evidence of two or three witnesses.
If he refuses to listen to them, tell it to the church.
And if he refuses to listen even to the church,
let him be to you as a Gentile and a tax collector.
Truly I say to you,
whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in heaven,
and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven.
Again I say to you,
if two of you agree on earth about anything they ask,
it will be done for them by my Father in heaven.
For where two or three are gathered in my name,
there am I among them.
Then Peter came up and said to him,
Lord, how often will my brother sin against me and I forgive him?
As many as seven times?
Jesus said to him,
I do not say to you seven times, but seventy times seven.
Therefore the kingdom of heaven may be compared to a king
who wished to settle accounts with his servants.
When he began to settle,
one was brought to him who owed him ten thousand talents.
And since he could not pay,
his master ordered him to be sold with his wife and children
and all that he had in payment to be made.
So the servant fell on his knees,
imploring him,
Have patience with me,
and I will pay you everything.
And out of pity for him,
the master of that servant released him
and forgave him the debt.
But when that same servant went out,
he found one of his fellow servants
who owed him a hundred denarii,
and seizing him,
he began to choke him, saying,
Pay what you owe.
So his fellow servant fell down and pleaded with him,
Have patience with me,
and I will pay you.
He refused,
and refused,
and went and put him in prison
until he should pay the debt.
When his fellow servants saw what had taken place,
they were greatly distressed,
and they went and reported to their master
all that had taken place.
Then his master summoned him and said to him,
You wicked servant,
I forgave you all that debt
because you pleaded with me,
and should not you have had mercy
on your fellow servant
as I had mercy on you?
And in anger his master delivered,
and delivered him to the jailers,
until he should pay all his debt.
But he did not even fall for your lies,
and will ever prevent you
And he did not even fall for your lies,
although he had enough
and also my heavenly father
will do to every one of you
if you do not forgive your brother
from your heart.
How will you forgive him?
Whether you forgive his brother
By loving him